嗨大家好，歡迎回到圖像處理的入門 Python 教學
hi everyone welcome back to the introductory python tutorials for image processing
在最後幾個視頻中，我們研究了自動編碼器
in the last couple of videos we looked at auto encoders
再來一個快速總結，自動編碼器
and again a quick summary auto encoders
根據定義，它們接受一個輸入
by definition they take an input
他們嘗試重建這些輸入
and they try to reconstruct that input
我們正試圖通過提供輸入來欺騙這些自動編碼器
and we are trying to trick these auto encoders by providing an input
比如說，一張圖片
you know like an image for example
以及預期輸出會有所不同
and the expected output to be something else
通過這樣做，我們嘗試使用自動編碼器
and by doing that we're trying to use auto encoders
或者你知道的
or you know for
或為特定應用如影像著色自訂自動編碼器
or customize auto encoders for certain applications like image colorization
或去噪
or denoising
我們目前的重點是看看這是否可以用於語意分割
and our focus right now is to see if that can be used for semantic segmentation
在上一個視頻中，我們意識到也許不是
and in the last video we realized that maybe not
我的意思是，結果在初看時看起來很好
i mean it the results look good on first you know on first look
但存在空間信息的丟失
but there is a loss of spatial information
這對於語意分割來說非常重要
which is very important for semantic segmentation
因為畢竟我們正在嘗試分類
because after all we are trying to classify
我們影像中的每一個像素
every pixel in our image
那麼在這段影片中，我們來學習一下單位
so in this video let's learn about units
以及它們如何與自動編碼器不同
and how they are different from an auto encoder
或
or
或許我應該將它表述為它們如何與自動編碼器相似
maybe i should have phrased it as how they are similar to autoencoder
自編碼器的限制是什麼
like what is the limitation of autoencoder
單位如何解決這一限制
and how do units fix that limitation
讓我們先了解一下這一點，所以首先讓我們
let's understand that so first of all let's
快速看一下我們的自動編碼器
have a quick look at our auto encoder
再次顯示一個大圖像
again a large image
漸漸變小
progressively goes down in size
但接著特徵數量增加
but then goes up in number of features
是的，這裡 128 256 512
yeah here 128 256 512
以此類推
and so on
從這個瓶頸開始，圖像將恢復到原始大小
and from from from this bottleneck it's going back up to the image's original size
如果你提供一張這樣的圖片作為輸入
so if you provide it with a image like this as input
如果你的預期輸出是相同的，那麼它會將輸入重新構建回來
and if your expected output is the same then it reconstructs the input back
但
but
如果你提供的預期輸出是這樣，那麼它應該會重建出類似這樣的東西
if you provide your expected output as this then it is expected to reconstruct something of this sort
但這就是我們從上一段視頻看到的內容
but then this is what we saw that from the last video right
所以這是我們所期望的
so this is what we expect
而這是我們看到的
and this is what we saw
看起來很棒
which looks great
初看時顏色都正確
on first look it got the colors right
它把一切都做對了
it got everything right it got
大部分的空間位置正確，除了
most of the spatial locations right except
這不是非常準確
it's not very accurate
當涉及到這些空間時
when it comes to these spatial
你會看到一切看起來
you see everything looks
有點模糊
like a bit blurred
它幾乎看起來像
it's almost looks like
這是上述圖像的高斯濾波版本
this is gaussian filtered version of this above image
這是模糊的圓形物體，再次發生
this is fuzzy rounded objects that is again happening
因為當你到達這裡時，它失去了所有的空間信息
because by the time you get down here it lost all of its spatial information
在這裡，你在第一次對話中擁有非常好的空間信息
that that you have from here at convo one you have very good spatial information right contu
稍微具體一點
a little bit concrete
但是到 con5 你失去了那個信息
but then up to con5 you lost that information
那麼我們如何獲得這些，我們如何保留這些特殊信息
so how do we gain that how do we retain this special information
這就是單元再次解決的問題，正如你可能已經意識到的
this is what unit solves again as you probably realized
所以讓我們以一種簡單的抽象方式來看看自動編碼器，現在不要去看
so let's look at the auto encoder in a nice abstract way right not look at
讓這變得像這個自動編碼器一樣複雜
make this as complicated as this autoencoder
再次是任何從大尺寸變小的東西
again is anything that goes from a large size small
然後在卷積層中再次變大
and then goes back up in in convolutional layers
所以
so
我們有這個編碼器部分，剩下的就是解碼器
we have this encoder part and the remaining is the decoder
對，如何有效保留空間資訊
right so how to retain spatial information well
如果我們取
what if we take
將這裡的空間資訊添加到解碼器層的下一部分
add the spatial information from here to the next part to the decoder layers
如果我們能夠將編碼器的空間資訊添加到解碼器的右側
what if we can take encoder spatial information add to decoder right
所以這正是
so this is exactly
我所說的
what i'm talking about
獲取空間資訊
take the spatial information
將其添加到解碼器中的功能資訊
add it to the feature information that you have in the decoder
當我說添加空間資訊時
when i say add spatial information
我的意思是取出這些功能
i mean the take the features
從編碼器
from the encoder
把它加到解碼器，這正是
add it to the decoder this is exactly
現在讓我們做這些箭頭
now let's let's make these arrows
這些箭頭是直的
these arrows straight
這就是我現在試圖以圖形方式做的全部
that's all i'm trying to do right now in a graphical way
如果我把這些弄直會發生什麼
how do i what happens if i make these straight
我要彎曲
i'm going to bend
將它彎成 U 形
this in a u shape
是的，這正是
yeah that's exactly
單位是什麼
what a unit is
所以我的編碼器仍然在那裡，我只是把這些連接直接連接了
so my encoder is still right there i just made these connections straight these connections straight
所以這有點彎曲，瓶頸就在這裡
so this is a bit bent with this bottleneck sitting down here
所以這圖完全一樣，這只是一種不同的表示方式
so it's exactly the same diagram by the way it's a different representation
所以我可以解釋
so i can justify
叫它單元
calling it unit
這部分基本上是我們的編碼器，您可以在這裡看到
this part is basically our encoder that you see here
這部分基本上是我們的解碼器，唯一的區別是這個
and this part is basically our decoder the only difference between this
這是這些輸入的串聯
and this is the concatenation of these input
來自這些層的輸入，就這樣，這就是簡而言之
inputs from these layers that's it this is in a nutshell
單元是什麼，你可以閱讀論文來獲得更多關於這方面的信息
what a unit is you can read the paper to get a lot more information about this
這是這篇論文
and this is the paper
來自 2015 年的生物醫學影像分割的卷積神經網絡
convolutional networks for biomedical image segmentation from 2015
儘管這是五六年前的
even though this is from five six years ago
概念仍然
the the concept still
規則，我應該說這仍然是語義分割的最佳方法
rules i should say this is still the best way of for semantic segmentation
現在只需了解
now just to understand
這稍微好一些，這是他們實際發布的原始圖像
this a bit better this is the original image that they actually published
在他們的論文中，輸入圖像為 572 x 572
in the in the in their paper with input images 572 by 572
等等，但這不重要，只需更仔細地查看這個表示
and so on but it doesn't matter just have a closer look in this representation
從輸入來看，你有兩個卷積層，藍色線條，藍色箭頭
going from the input you have two convolution layers the blue line the blue arrow
代表三乘三的卷積
represents a three by three convolution
使用 ReLU 激活函數的操作
operation with a relu activation function
好的
okay
每條藍線都是一個 2D 卷積
so each blue line is a con convolution 2d con
或 3D
or 3d
如果你想將這個擴展到 3D
if you want to extend this to 3d
但我們就假設這是一個卷積
but let's just say this is a convolution
隨後是
followed by
無線電啟用卷積與鐵路啟用
radio activation convolution with railway activation
在這之後，你將進行最大池化
after this you're doing max pooling
2 乘 2 最大池化
2 by 2 max pooling
當你進行 2x2 的最大池化時，輸入圖像的大小會縮小
what happens when you do max pooling 2x2 the input image size goes down
所以你的輸入圖像不再是 570
so instead of your input image being 570
或其他什麼
or something
現在它是 284 乘 284
now it is 284 by 284 right there
好的
okay
並且過濾器的數量從 64 增加到 128，再到 256，再到 512
and the number of filters are going up from 64 to 128 to 256 to 512
完全相同的結構我們在自動編碼器中看到過
exactly the same structure we saw as part of our auto encoder
好的
okay
綠色箭頭表示上卷積，這可以是上採樣
and the green arrows represent up convolution this can be upscaling up sampling sorry
或上卷積轉換 2D 反向
or up convolution convert 2d transpose
這些是綠色箭頭
and these are the green arrows
然後你會看到藍色箭頭，它們是傳遞的
and then you see the blue arrows that are conve
這裡的兩者都是解碼器的一部分
both here as part of decoder
以及這裡作為編碼器的一部分
and here as part of encoder
然後你會得到你的輸出分段地圖
and then you get your output segmented map
現在讓我們來看一下 256x256
now let's look at this for 256 by 256
因為這樣很方便，我們一直在使用 256 張圖像
because it makes it easy we have been working with 256 images
所以讓我們看看這裡的相同結構
so let's look at the same structure here
好的
okay
所以我的輸入圖像是 256 乘 256
so my input image is 256 by 256
一個通道
one channel
假設我的輸入圖像不是彩色的，而是灰階的
let's just say my input image is not color it's grayscale
我的意思是可以是三個，但現在假設是只有一個
i mean it can be three but for now let's say one
在前兩層卷積之後
after the first two convolution layers
我在那裡有 64 個過濾器
i have 64 filters right there
然後我執行 2x2 的最大池化
and then i perform max pooling 2 by 2
這意味著我的 256 變成 128。
which means my 256 becomes 128.
所以這個維度是 128 乘 128
so this dimension is 128 by 128
然後我們使用多少個濾波器進行卷積操作
and then we perform convolutional operation with how many filters
現在 128 個過濾器
now 128 filters
然後進行最大池化
and then max pooling
這意味著我的 128 變成 64
which means my 128 becomes 64
然後我將濾波器的數量加倍到 256
and then i double the number of filters to 256
我一直做到這裡為止
and i do that all the way up to down here
在這裡我有 1024
where i have 1024
功能
features
並且僅在我的影像尺寸中為 16x16
and only 16 by 16 in terms of my image dimensions
現在我想上升
now i want to go up
從 1024 我去戰鬥得很好，為什麼
from 1024 i go to fight well why
因為我有二乘二的上卷積意思
because i have up convolution of two by two meaning
或把這看作上採樣
or think of this as up sampling
好的，抱歉，這裡的大小應該是 32 乘 32，這就是我所說的
okay sorry the size here would be 32 by 32 this is what i meant
好的
yeah
所以從 16 x 16 開始，我的尺寸會變成 32 x 32
so from 16 by 16 my size would be 32 by 32
因為我有 2 x 2 的上採樣。
because i have an up sampling of 2 by 2.
好的
okay
並且我從 10 24 個濾波器增加到 512 個
and i'm going from 10 24 filters to 512
然後是兩次卷積
and then two convolutions
相同的東西重複
same thing repeating
向上卷積
up convolution
所以你的大小從 32 增加到 64。
so your size goes from 32 to 64.
然後是卷積
and then convolutions
以此類推
and so on
現在
now
串接在哪裡出現
where does the concatenation come into picture
所以我們來看看這個
so let's just look at this
因為那邊不太擁擠對吧
because it's not too busy up there right
所以你有
so you have
這個操作後你會有 128
after this operation you have 128
就在那裡的過濾器功能
filters features right there
好的，從 256 你會降到 128
okay from 256 you're going to 128
但是我們將從這裡添加的 128 個數據合併到這些數據中
but then we are adding the 128 that are coming from here to these right there
好的
okay
所以這就是我們正在串聯的內容
so that's what we are concatenating
然後進行我們的卷積操作
and then comes our convolution operation
然後我們進行上採樣
and then comes our up up sampling right there
還有卷積操作，濾波器數量為 128，顯然是對的
and the convolution operation with a filters number of filters of 128 obviously right
所以這裡有 128 加 128
so here you have 128 plus 128
但接下來的卷積，我們是說，把它轉換成 128 個濾波器
but then the convolution right there we are saying that hey convert that into 128 filters
所以在卷積操作之後，你會有 128 個
so after the convolution operation you have 128
影像大小為 128 x 128。
and the image size is 128 128.
所以這個藍色的
so this blue
就是那些以藍色顯示的部分
the ones that are represented in blue right there
他們代表來自解碼器的特徵
they are representing the features coming from the decoder
和那個透明的
and the one that is transparent
像這裡的白色方框，這裡有來自這裡的特徵
box like the white box right here there are the features coming from here
這意味著這個白色框包含我們非常需要的空間資訊
that means this white box contains spatial information that's much needed for us
而這個藍色框包含
and this blue box contains
用來理解特徵所需的特徵資訊。我希望這樣能讓你明白
the feature information that's needed to understand the features i hope this makes sense
所以我們在離開時做的完全相同
so we are doing exactly the same on the way out
最後
and finally
因為這是一個，你知道的
because this is a you know
一個通道的影像，我在這裡輸出，或在這個例子中我的 y 只有一個通道
one channel image again i'm outputting here or my y in this case has one channel
這就是我的輸出
so that's my output right there
你怎麼編碼？非常簡單，就像你在這裡看到的一樣
how do you code it very simple exactly the way you see it here
對不起，我的輸入是 256 到 56 1，那是我的輸入
excuse me my input is 256 to 56 1 that's my input
然後進行兩次卷積操作，每次都是三乘三
then comes two convolution operations right with three by three
和 Rayleigh
and rayleigh
可轉換性 可轉換性
convertibility convertivity
有多少個濾鏡
how many filters
64 個過濾器適用於我的操作 64 個過濾器 64 個過濾器
64 filters right for my operation 64 filters 64 filters
三乘三，您可以在這裡輸入三或三乘三
three by three you can just type three here or three by three
這取決於你
it's up to you
它接受 Keras 也接受
it accepts both keras accepts both
這是三乘三的
that's three by three that's
這表示的是
what this is indicating
然後激活函數是 ReLU
and then activation is relu
我會將填充設定為相同
i'm gonna do padding equals to same
這樣我的輸出大小會相同
so my output is the same size
這裡的輸出與這個輸入 256 256 相同大小
output here is the same size as this input 256 256.
我不認為原始論文
i don't think the original paper
做到了這一點，因此尺寸有所變化
did that that's why there is a change in size
從 572 變到 570 再變到 568
from 572 to 570 to 568
這是我所想的
that's what i think
在我們的情況下，我們就輸出吧
in our case let's just put output
填充等於相同
padding equals to same
這樣我們就不會丟失任何信息
so we don't lose any information there
好的
okay
所以這些是兩個卷積層
so these are the two con layers
然後是最大池化，對吧？兩個卷積層之後是兩乘兩的最大池化
then comes max pooling right two con then comes max pooling of watt two by two
兩兩池化的 2D 最大池化
max pooling 2d of pool size two by two
接下來的兩層卷積層 128 最大池化 1.28
next two convolution layers 128 max pooling 1.28
最大池化然後 256 最大池化
max pooling then 256 max pooling
好的
okay
所以這部分應該非常簡單，就是編碼器部分
so this part should be pretty straightforward the encoder part
這是基數 1024
and this is the base 1024
就在那裡
right there
你用這個 1024 做什麼？
what do you do with this 1024
現在我們需要反過來做
now we need to go the other way around
好的
okay
所以以這個作為輸入，以 b1 作為輸入
so with that as input with b1 as input
就在那裡，那是我的輸入
right there that's my input
好的，我想進行一次卷積操作
okay i would like to do a convolution operation
對，我想進行一次卷積操作
right i would like to a convolution operation
對不起
excuse me
然後連接連接
and then concatenate concatenate
什麼 s4
what s4
和 d1
and d1
s4 是什麼
what is s4
和 d1
and d1
所以
so
哦，我沒有處理好，我在串聯
oh i'm not putting well i'm concatenating
這個
this
和這個在下一步中一起串聯
and this together in the next step once you concatenate
兩個卷積運算
two convolution operations
戰鬥閥的連續性
contudy continuity of fight valve
是的，那裡有 512
yeah a 512 right there
然後來到
then comes
另一個卷積操作
what another convolution operation
好的，在 d1 上
okay on d1
所以這裡的輸出是另一個卷積，你看到的是二乘二的卷積
so the output here another convolution right there you see up convolution two by two
然後你將這兩個連接在一起，這正是
and then you concatenate these two that's exactly
我們在這裡所做的
what we do here
將這兩個連接起來
concatenate those two
然後再進行兩次卷積操作 con con
and then perform two more convolution operations con con
所以這會重複
so this repeats
一路上
all the way
在你獲得輸出後
after you get your output
所以我希望這可以澄清你對單位的任何疑問
so i hope this this clears any any doubts that you have about unit
但至少為我們建立了一個良好的基礎，以便理解單位
but at least establishes a nice basement for us to understand units
在接下來的幾個影片中，我們會逐步進行
as we go along in the next few videos
讓我們跳到程式碼，複製並貼上這個
let's jump to the code copy paste this
並查看 model.summary
and see just model.summary
好的
okay
所以這就是我所做的，我只是導入了相關的
so here you go all i did is imported the relevant
這裡的庫，順便提一下，來自 keras.layers
libraries here by the way from keras.layers
事實上，一個好的
in fact a good
如果你正在使用 TensorFlow 2 或更高版本，建議使用 TensorFlow dot
practice if you're working on tensorflow 2 or later is do intense tensor flow dot
cash dot layers
因為這可能是處理這種情況的最佳方法
because that's probably the best way to deal with that
和你需要記住的一點是，如果你這麼做，你需要對所有 Keras 進行這樣的處理
and one thing you
好的，你不能混合使用，否則會出現一些奇怪的錯誤
have to remember is if you do that you do that for all keras
okay you cannot mix and match it throws some weird error
然後你會花一整天試圖弄明白那個錯誤的意思
and you'll spend all day trying to figure out what that error means
所以從 keras.layers
so from keras.layers
我們得到的是 con 2d
we are getting con 2d
最大池化
max pooling
上採樣 連接 記住
up sampling concatenate remember
這些都是我們需要的東西，我還在導入
these are all the things that we need i'm also importing
2d 轉置以便替換
con 2d transpose in case you want to replace
用這個替換你的上採樣
your up sampling with this
或者你知道，僅僅做一些測試批量正則化丟棄
or you know just to do some testing batch normalization dropout
而且我甚至不確定我們是否在使用 Lambda
and i'm not even sure if we are using lambda
但
but
是的，我在那裡不使用 Lambda
yeah i'm not using lambda right there
但
but
我們來進口這些，我覺得我們需要連接
let's go ahead and import these i think we need to connect
目前執行時間可以不需要 GPU
and for now the run time can be you don't need gpu
因為我們不會執行其他任務
because we are not going to run anything other than other
我的意思是我們不會訓練模型
i mean we are not going to train a model
那麼我們接著來導入我們的庫
so let's go ahead and import our libraries
然後這段代碼正是
and then this code is exactly
我在演示中展示給你的部分，對吧，我是說你有貢獻
what i showed you as part of the presentation right i mean you have contri
現在
now
我更正一下，這不完全是在卷積層之間，我加了一個 dropout 層
i correct myself this is not exactly in between the convolution layers i added a dropout layer
如果你
if you
如果你，整個重點是我想讓你看到的是
if you the whole point is i want to show you that it's
是的，結構，原始結構顯示了你 con con 最大池化
yeah the structure the original structure shows you con con max polling
你可以添加批次正規化
you can add batch normalization
在這些欄位之間，您可以添加，您可以添加
as part of in between these columns you can add you can add
我討厭這個東西，您可以添加丟失值
i hate this thing you can add dropout
您知道，作為正則化項，因此您可以在這些之間添加一些
you know just as a regularization term so you can add some of these in between
但是整體結構是你有 con
but the overall structure is you have con
con 最大池化 con con 最大池化 我在中間添加了 dropout con con 最大池化
con max pooling con con max pulling i'm adding dropout in between con con max pooling
和昂貴的路徑在這個例子中，除了僅僅執行卷積
and expensive path in this example instead of just performing convolution
操作，我認為這很重要
operation i think this is important
所以讓我切換回來
so let me switch back
所以我可以向你展示這裡，我們正在使用 con con 最大池化
so i can show you this right here right here we are using con con max pooling
在我的例子中，在卷積層之間我加入了 dropout
in my example between the convolution layers i added dropout
只是為了確保我的模型不會過擬合，這就是擴展路徑中我進行了卷積操作
just to make sure my model doesn't over fit that's it in the expansion path i did convolution operation
然後就在那裡進行了上採樣
and then did the up sampling right there
可以調整到那個大小
okay to that size
我做了卷積運算
i did convolution operation
將圖像上採樣到特定大小，然後進行卷積
up sampling to that specific size followed by the convolution
操作正確，所以連接
operation right so con
然後當你做 2d 轉置時，卷積就會在那裡
and then up sample when you do con 2d transpose the conv is right there
轉置是內建的
and the transpose is built in
是的，所以你不會在兩個不同的步驟中進行這個
yeah so you don't you don't do this in two different steps
所以讓我們回到之前的內容
so let's jump back
那麼這樣
so there you go
所以這裡我有 convert2d 轉置
so here i have convert2d transpose
然後我在進行串接
and then i'm concatenating
哦，上帝，幫助
oh god the help
然後我在串接
and then i'm concatenating
然後另一個 con 2d
and then another con 2d
然後另一位貢獻者也非常相似
and then another contributor right very similar
所以這就是
so this is
我們是如何建立的
how we built
然後我嘗試去
and then i'm trying to
印出 model dot summary
print out model dot summary
讓我們繼續
and let us go ahead
並將摘要列印出來，這就是我們的單元模型
and print the summary out and there you go here is our unit model
所以一旦你理解了結構，建立單元其實非常簡單
so building a unit is once you understand the structure this is very simple actually
實際上，你可以使用特定功能來定義這裡的單元
in fact you can use specific functions to define the unit here
如果你看到重複的內容
if you see what is repeating
連續性掉線造成的最大輪詢
continuity dropout contributing max polling
相反的掉線，相反的最大輪詢
contrary dropout contrary max polling
所以這整個東西是一個區塊
so this entire thing is one block
這整個東西是另一個區塊，這是另一個區塊，對吧
this entire thing is another block this is another block right
這樣你就可以僅為卷積區塊定義一個函數
so you can define a function only for the convolution block
然後只需改變濾波器的數量，就是這樣
and then just change the number of filters that's it
因為這是唯一會改變的東西，所以如果你想要更乾淨的代碼
because that's the only thing that's changing right so if you want a cleaner code
這是一種更好的做事方式
that's a much better way of doing things
好的
okay
所以這是一個簡單的介紹
so this is a quick introduction of
一般來說，我一直承諾要談論上採樣與 2D 轉置卷積
the unit in general i keep promising to talk about up sampling versus con 2d transpose
我保證我會在下一個影片中做到這一點
i i promise that i'll do that in the next video
我覺得你首先了解這點非常重要
i thought it's very important for you to understand this first
這樣你就知道我們所說的上採樣是什麼意思
so you know what we mean by up sampling
以及 2D 轉置
and con 2d transpose
然後討論這兩個，所以請繼續關注下一個視頻
and then talk about these these two so please stay tuned for the next video
並訂閱這個頻道，謝謝
and subscribe to this channel thank you